

John R Clayton

SCIENTIST · VECTOR-BORNE DISEASES

ADDRESS REDACTED

\$\cup +1 (559) 555-1212 | \$\sup \text{REDACTED} | \$\mathbf{O}\$ REDACTED | \$\mathbf{G}\$ REDACTED | \$\mathbf{Q}\$ REDACTED | \$\m

"Nothing in biology makes sense except in the light of evolution"



Summary

I am a molecular biologist by training with 15 years of experience working on the genetics of disease vector mosquitoes. I have a PhD in Molecular Microbiology & Immunology from Johns Hopkins University. A California native, I was born and raised near Blythe, in the remote expanses of the Sonoran desert. Over the years, I've held more than a dozen positions in the US States of California, Georgia and Maryland as well as Heidelberg, Germany and Strasbourg, France. In addition to being a native speaker of English, I have a working knowledge of French, Spanish & German.

Education

Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health Department of Molecular Microbiology & Immunology

Baltimore, MD 2003-2010

Doctorate

Dissertation: Transduction of Virulence Factors by Alphaviruses in Vertebrate and Invertebrate Models of Infection

Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health Department of International Health

Baltimore, MD

Certificate, Vaccine Science & Policy 2003-2005

University of California Department of Molecular & Cell Biology

Berkelev, CA

BACCALAUREATE 1996-2000

Emphasis: Genetics & Development

Work Experience _____

Université de Strasbourg Institut de Biologie Moléculaire et Cellulaire

Strasbourg, France

POST-DOCTORAL RESEARCHER 2011-2015

As a fellow with the French *Institut national de la santé et de la recherche médicale* (INSERM), I successfully developed reagents to silence single alleles of polymorphic genes in *An. gambiae* to determine the contribution of each allele to susceptibility to *Plasmodium* infection in the mosquito. My other main research project involved the characterization of a transgenic strain of *An. gambiae* that produces small piwi-like RNAs derived from its integrated transgene locus, causing them to become hyper-susceptible to *Plasmodium* infection.

Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health Department of Molecular Microbiology & Immunology

Baltimore, MD

Pre-doctoral Researcher 2003-2010

My dissertation research largely involved the characterization of and acquired, sequence-specific anti-viral resistance phenotype observed in *Aedes aegypti* during Alphavirus infection. I also developed a recombinant, mosquitocidal Alphavirus expressing the pro-apoptotic gene *reaper* and evaluated its suitability as a potential biocontrol agent. Another project involved comparative analysis of the Bunyavirus virulence factor NSs in mice and mosquitoes.

European Molecular Biology Laboratory Kafatos Group

Heidelberg, Germany

Post-baccalaureate Researcher 2002-2003

While working in the Kafatos lab I developed a transgenic strain of *An. gambiae* expressing a fluorescent reporter specifically in midgut epithelial cells that had been invaded by the malaria parasite. In parallel, I performed functional analysis of immunity genes and identified a role for the mosquito NF-RB-like transcription factor *REL2* during *Plasmodium* infection.

Atlanta, GA

EMERGING INFECTIOUS DISEASES FELLOW 2000-2002

While an EID fellow at the CDC, I invented the breakthrough transformation method for An. qambiae still in use today. I also characterized the transgenic strains we obtained while working with both P. vivax and P. falciparum malaria parasites in a BSL-2 environment. Field work opportunities included surveillance for West Nile Virus and assisting in CDC's emergency response during the 2001 Anthrax bioterror crisis.

University of California

Department of Integrative Biology

Berkeley, CA

RESEARCH ASSISTANT 1998-1999

While in the Brent Mishler's laboratory I evaluated the utility of RNA secondary structures to reconstruct deep phylogenies of green plants.

Languages

Spoken

English

• French

 Spanish • German **Programming**

 R • MFX

Python

Bash

Skills

Laboratory

· Expert at a wide array of molecular biology, biochemistry & genetics techniques

DNA/RNA/protein extraction/purification **aPCR** RT-PCR SNP genotyping Southern blot RNA Blot SDS-PAGE small RNA blot cell culture cell transfection immunofluorescence microscopy plaque assay micropipette design microinjection DNA sequence analysis Sanger sequencing Illumina DNA sequencing small RNAseq molecular cloning gene synthesis agarose gel electrophoresis ultracentrifugation

Entomology

· Expert at all aspects of cultivating and maintaining colonies of Anopheles & Aedes mosquitoes

larval feeding & splitting adult cultivation egg bleaching vacuum hatching pupal & adult sexing stock maintenance single-pair mating fluorescence screening of transgenic strains midgut dissection salivary gland dissection ovary dissection hemolymph extraction blood feeding genetic crossing

Software

• Expert user of the Microsoft Windows, Apple Mac OS X, Darwin/BSD Unix and Linux operating systems

Galaxy (workflow management system) **DNAStar Lasergene** Primer Express Adobe Acrobat Adobe PageMaker MS Word MS Excel MS Powerpoint Adobe Photoshop Adobe Illustrator Adobe Premiere ffmpeg TFXShop

Teaching Experience

Université de Strasbourg

TEACHING ASSISTANT

Institut de Biologie Moléculaire et Cellulaire

Strasbourg, France

MASTER'S STUDENT MENTOR 2011-2015

Technical oversight of three master's level students with projects related to functional analysis of *Anopheles* genes during malaria infection and *in* vivo RNA interference in Anopheles and Drosophila.

Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health Department of Molecular Microbiology & Immunology

Baltimore, MD

TEACHING ASSISTANT

Graduate student instructor for Molecular Entomology. Lead exam reviews for students before midterm and final.

University of California Berkeley, CA

2000

Undergraduate student instructor for Health and Medical ethics.

Honors & Awards Scholarship Dr. Lloyd and Mae Rozeboom Scholarship in Medical Entomology 2004 Baltimore, MD Emerging Infectious Diseases Laboratory Research Fellowship 2000 **Fellowship** Atlanta, GA 1999 **Travel Grant** Deep Green Travel Grant for the XVI International Botanical Congress Berkeley, CA Scholarship 1996 Blythe Jaycees Scholarship Blythe, CA **Training Courses** • Chemical and biological waste disposal practices and safety training **Ethics & Safety** · Radioactive isotope certification and safety training · Ethical use of vertebrate animals in research training **Extracurricular Activities Phi Kappa Tau Fraternity** Berkeley, CA 1997-2000 MEMBER, NU CHAPTER As member of the fraternity, I held the positions of Scholarship Chair and Secretary as well as serving on the chapter Executive Committee. The Daily Californian Berkeley, CA PRODUCTION INTERN 1998 Responsible for daily page layout **UC Berkeley Intercollegiate Bowling Team** Berkeley, CA 1996-1997 Selected for the university bowling team as a first semester freshman **PVHS Class of 1996** Blythe, CA 1995-1996 **PRESIDENT** Elected to serve as Senior class president **PVHS Yellowjackets Golf Team** Blythe, CA VARSITY LETTERMAN 1993-1996 Played on varsity golf team for four years The Stinger Blythe, CA **EDITOR** 1993-1994 Features Editor and Advertisement Sales for our student newspaper **Extracurricular Employment Skates on The Bay** Berkeley, CA WAITER 2000 Waitstaff at a seafood restaurant in The Berkeley Marina **Mazzini Trattoria** Berkeley, CA BUSSER 1999-2000 Service staff at a fine Northern Italian restaurant **Robinson Farms** Blythe, CA FORKLIFT OPERATOR 1996-1997 Loaded tractor-trailers during melon season **Desert Security Farms** Blythe, CA LABORER 1994 Tarped hay stacks **Blythe Drug Company** Blythe, CA

1993-1996

Duties included customer service, sales, inventory and deliveries

SALES CLERK

Personal Interests
In my spare time, I like to travel and visit monuments, museums and parks. Activities I enjoy include bowling, cycling, golf, tennis, volleyball and poker. I also enjoy dining, cinema, theater and classical as well as contemporary live music performances.

Published Research
Photographs
Patents
Research Presentations

Courses Attended _____

Posters _____

Scientific Meetings _____

Blythe, CA

Double "R" Vending